Guide to the Stanford University, Public Affairs Office Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Public Affairs Office records
1960-1980
SC0105
Stanford University. Public Affairs Office.
9.25 Linear feet
The collection consists of correspondence, memoranda, press releases, photographs, maps, and other documents concerning various events and controversies dealt with by the Public Affairs Office, 1960-1980. Subjects include the Stanford Linear Accelerator Center, Stanford Industrial Park, Ladera Dam and flood control on the San Francisquito Creek, Stanford in Britain overseas campus, dismissal of H. Bruce Franklin, ROTC on campus, the Winds of Freedom Foundation, and the inauguration of university president Kenneth S. Pitzer. Includes audio tapes of a press conference on KZSU with Stanford President Richard W. Lyman, May 30, 1972; and of a talk by John Kaplan to the Los Angeles Stanford Club on the Bakke case.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer, Office of University Relations, 1973-1983.
Information about Access
The materials are open for research use.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
The University Relations Office acted as liaison between the University and the public. The office was renamed the Public Affairs Office in December 1974 and was enlarged to include federal, state, and community government relations as well as other University relations activities.
Description of the Collection
The collection consists of correspondence, memoranda, press releases, photographs, maps, and other documents concerning various events and controversies dealt with by the Public Affairs Office, 1960-1980. Subjects include the Stanford Linear Accelerator Center, Stanford Industrial Park, Ladera Dam and flood control on the San Francisquito Creek, Stanford in Britain overseas campus, dismissal of H. Bruce Franklin, ROTC on campus, the Winds of Freedom Foundation, and the inauguration of university president Kenneth S. Pitzer. Includes audio tapes of a press conference on KZSU with Stanford President Richard W. Lyman, May 30, 1972; and of a talk by John Kaplan to the Los Angeles Stanford Club on the Bakke case.
Access Terms
Bakke, Allan Paul.; Brigham Young University.; Fagan, Elmer.; Franklin, H. Bruce (Howard Bruce), 1934-; Kaplan, John, 1929-1989.; Kennedy, Donald, 1931-; KZSU (Radio station: Stanford, Calif.); Lyman, Richard W., 1923-2012.; Pitzer, Kenneth S., (Kenneth Sanborn), 1914-1997; Stanford Linear Accelerator Center; Stanford University. Public Affairs Office.; Stanford University. Stanford in Britain.; Stanford University. Summer Festival.; Sterling, J. E. Wallace, (John Ewart Wallace), 1906-1985; United States. Army. Reserve Officers' Training Corps.; Governor Stanford Locomotive.; Ladera Dam (Calif.); San Francisquito Creek (Calif.) --Flood control.
Collection Contents
- Records, 1960-1973; Series 1
  - Stanford Linear Accelerator Center - powerline dispute, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes schematic landscape design - Stanford Linear Accelerator. General plan building and End Station area. 1962 July 6; two informational pamphlets about SLAC.
  - SLAC powerline dispute, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Includes transcript of hearing by Joint Committee on Atomic Energy. Hearing on plans for supplying the electric energy requirements of the Stanford Linear Accelerator Project, SLAC - 1964 January 29; notebook summarizing the materials on the powerline controversy from 1964 January 16 to 1964 February 7. Includes copies of letters of principals involved in the controversy and relevant press releases, photographs and clippings.
  - SLAC powerline dispute, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes Paul McCloskey's Memorandum to the Board of Trustees re: proposed Searsville powerline compromise, 1964 February 13; abstract of talk by W.K.H. Panofsky to SLAC staff on "Powerline situation", 1964 March 5; press releases on the powerline dispute, 1964 March 23.
  - SLAC powerline dispute, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Includes photographs of the poles and sites in question.
  - SLAC powerline dispute, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes transcript of news conference conducted at site of SLAC with Chairman of the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission, Stanford Provost and Vice-President, Director of SLAC and the Vice-President of Commercial Operations, Pacific Gas and Electric Company, 1964 April 2.
  - SLAC powerline dispute, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes SLAC's collection of newspaper clippings re: the powerline controversy.
  - Ampex annexation dispute - Extending of the industrial park, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes miscellaneous documents re: Stanford's land development program, 1960-1961; miscelleaneous publications containing information on the Ampex controversy, 1960-1961; photographs of Coyote Hill, 1960.
  - Ladera Dam controversy - San Francisquito creek flood control, 1961-1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes brief presented to the Board of Engineers for Rivers and Harbors, Washington DC, stating Stanford's position on the Ladera Dam project proposed by the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, 1961 October 18; statement by Stanford Trustees relating Stanford's position and reasons for opposing the Ladera Dam project, 1961 October 19; TL Copy. To Dr. Sterling from Thomas H. Kuchel, U.S. Senator, on the progress of the San Francisquito project, 1962 February 23; a copy of a letter from Major General Keith Barney stating the reasons the army recommended the project over Stanford's objections 1962 February 8; confidential report to the Stanford Trustees on the status of the Ladera Dam project, 1962 February 27 with cover letter from the Director of University Relations, Lyle M. Nelson; confidential memorandum to Dwight Adams of the Stanford Business Office from Ray K. Linsley, Dept. of Civil Engineering re: San Francisquito creek flood control, 1963 July 9; press release summarizing the alternatives to the Ladera Dam, issued by Stanford's University Relations office, 1963 October 15.
  - Ladera Dam controversy - San Francisquito creek flood control, 1961-1967 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes reconnaissance report on the floods of 1967 January 21-24; Santa Clara Flood Control and Water District, 1967 January.
  - Ladera Dam controversy, 1961-1973 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Includes clippings and publications concerning Ladera Dam controversy.
  - Ladera Dam controversy, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Includes maps of the area involved in the controversy.
- Records, 1961-1966; Series 2
  Acquired in 1978 July
  - Athletics, 1963-1966 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Exchanges between the Athletics Department and University Relations
  - Communications Committee, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Correspondence and miscellaneous documents relating to attempts to survey alumni opinion and to bring a closer working relationship between "fund raisers" and "friend raisers" during the PACE campaign
  - Disaster Council, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Miscellaneous documents regarding the Civil Defense Disaster Plan
  - Professor Elmer Fagan, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Correspondence and miscellaneous documents regarding the retirement dinner given for Fagan, professor of economics [Public finance and taxation] at Stanford, 1928-1961.
  - Governor Stanford Locomotive (Engine #1), 1963 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Correspondence, newsclippings related to the loan of the Gov. Stanford to the Locomotive History Society for exhibit in San Francisco and its removal from the Stanford Museum.
  - KZSU Radio, Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Student radio station at Stanford
  - KZSU Radio, 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Liquor, 1962-1966 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Sharon Heights license application
  - Liquor, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Correspondence, etc. relating to sale of liquor near campus
  - Liquor, 1963-1966 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Stanford in Britain, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Press conference
  - Stanford in Britain, 1966 January (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Stanford in Britain, 1966 February (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Stanford in Britain, 1966 May-June (Box 4, Folder 7)
    The above four folders relate to the dedication of the first Stanford in Britain site, Harlaxton Manor, Grantham, Lincolnshire, 1966 April 16.
  - Student-Faculty advisory, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Correspondence and newsclippings related to the push for student self-government, beginning with the dismissal of Dean of Women, Lucile Allen.
  - Summer festivals, 1964-1966 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Correspondence and newsclippings relating to Stanford's very successful summer festivals, including Shakespeare and Mozart performances.
  - Summer festivals, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Twenty questions, 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Correspondence and miscellaneous documents relating to the effort to arm PACE volunteers with answers to recurring questions from donors.
  - White House conference on education, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Correspondence and other documents, including a transcript of proceedings, relating to this conference, held at Stanford (Lyle Nelson, coordinator; Bob Byers, publicist)
  - White memorial plaza, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Invitation to the dedication of the plaza and its fountain and artists drawings.
  - Winds of Freedom foundation, 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Winds of Freedom foundation, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    The above two folders of correspondence and other documents relate to the first organized effort by conservative alumni to curb "rampant" liberalism at Stanford.
- Records, 1969-1978; Series 3
  Received 1980 June
  - Brigham Young University (BYU): University Human Relations committee, Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    "The Brigham Young Decision" summary by Andrew Doty, and other correspondence.
  - BYU: Brigham Young University issue, 1969 January-1970 January (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - BYU: Pitzer form letters (DTC), 1970 January 12 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - BYU, 1970 January (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - BYU, 1970 February-April (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - BYU, 1976-1978 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    With some background to the problem
- Records, 1960-1980; Series 4
  Acquired in July 1983
  - SLAC dedication, 1967 September 9 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - SLAC, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - SLAC, 1966 April-December (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - SLAC Status report, 1966 June (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - SLAC, 1965 October-1966 March (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - SLAC, 1965 September (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - SLAC, 1965 August (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - SLAC, 1965 July (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - SLAC, 1965 June 10-30 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - SLAC, 1965 June 1-10 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - SLAC, 1965 May (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - SLAC, 1965 March-April (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - SLAC, 1965 January-February (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - SLAC, 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - SLAC Power, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - SLAC, 1964 October-December (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - SLAC, 1964 June-September (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - SLAC, 1964 May (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - SLAC, 1964 April (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - SLAC Power problems, 1964-1970 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - SLAC, 1964 March (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - SLAC, 1964 February (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - SLAC, 1964 January (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - SLAC, 1963 November-December (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - SLAC, 1963 October (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - SLAC, 1963 September (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - SLAC, 1963 August (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - SLAC, 1963 July (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - SLAC, 1963 June (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - SLAC, 1963 May (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - SLAC, 1963 April (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - SLAC, 1963 January-March (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - SLAC, 1962 July-December (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - SLAC, 1962 January-June (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - SLAC, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - SLAC, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Two cassette tapes, 1972 May 30 and undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
    : R.W. Lyman - Weekly Press Conference KZSU, 1972 May 30; Robert M. Brown - KZSU, 1972 May 30 and Public Affairs - John Kaplan to L.A. Stanford Club on Bakke case
  - Ladera Dam, Masters for copies, Undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Ladera Dam, Governor Brown, Undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Ladera Dam, Preliminary Economic Review, Undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Ladera Dam, SLAC letter: Panofsky/Army Engineers, Undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Ladera Dam photos, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Ladera Dam clippings, Undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Ladera Dam data sheets, Undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Ladera Dam, 1960-1961 September (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Ladera Dam, 1961 October (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Ladera Dam, Report to Board of R and H, 1961 October 18 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Ladera Dam, 1961 November-December (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Ladera Dam, Report to Board of R and H, 1961, December 11 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Ladera Dam, 1962 January-February (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Ladera Dam, 1962 March (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Ladera Dam, 1962 April (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Ladera Dam, 1962 May-July (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Ladera Dam, 1962 August-December (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Ladera Dam, 1963 January-April (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Ladera Dam, 1963 May-August (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Ladera Dam, 1963 September-October (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Ladera Dam, summary, 1963 October (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Ladera Dam, 1963 November-December (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Ladera Dam, 1964 January-May (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Ladera Dam, 1964 June-September (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Ladera Dam, 1964 October-December (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Ladera Dam, 1965 January-March (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Ladera Dam, 1965 April-May (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Ladera Dam, 1965 June-August (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Ladera Dam, 1965 September-December (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - Ladera Dam, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - Ladera Dam, 1967 January-February (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - Ladera Dam, 1967 March-April (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Ladera Dam, 1967 May (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - Ladera Dam, 1967 June-September (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - Ladera Dam, 1967 October-December (Box 9, Folder 35)
  - Ladera Dam, 1968 January-June (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Ladera Dam, 1968 July-December (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Ladera Dam, 1969 January-June (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Ladera Dam, clippings: extra copies, Undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Ladera Dam, notes; names, Undated (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Ladera Dam, maps, Undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Ladera Dam, technical subcommittee reports, Undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Ladera Dam, highlights, 1961-1966 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Ladera Dam, map, Undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Ladera Dam, San Francisquito Creek Flood Control, Undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Bruce Franklin injunction, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Bruce Franklin court rulings, 1973-1980 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Bruce Franklin information, 1971 January-September (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Bruce Franklin information, beginning 1972 January 18 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Bruce Franklin correspondence, 1971 April-December (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Bruce Franklin correspondence, 1971 January-March (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Bruce Franklin correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Bruce Franklin, Complaints: Letter Lists, through 1972 November (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - ROTC, 1973 June (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - ROTC Mann Committee Report, Undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - ROTC general correspondence, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - ROTC at Stanford (pca), 1970-1973 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - ROTC general information, 1971 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - ROTC, 1970 June 16-30 and later (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - ROTC, 1970 May 16-31 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - ROTC, 1970 May 1-15 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - ROTC general file: information and correspondence, 1970 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Inauguration of Kenneth S. Pitzer as University President, correspondence file, 1968-1971 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Inauguration committee, circa 1969 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Inauguration plan, circa 1969 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Pitzer, K.S. - remarks at his inauguration, circa 1969 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Gardner, John W. - remarks at inauguration, circa 1969 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Inauguration of Kenneth S. Pitzer as University President, Invitation and program, circa 1969 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Inauguration of Kenneth S. Pitzer as University President, Order of exercises, circa 1969 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Inauguration of Kenneth S. Pitzer as University President, Miscellaneous items, circa 1969 (Box 13, Folder 8)